Guide to the Peter E. Palmquist Collection of Photography and Photographic Formats
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Peter E. Palmquist collection of photography and photographic formats
1838-1999
WA Photos 495
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
57.6
(186 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
This collection documents photography and photographic formats, circa 1846-1999, which Peter Palmquist collected from 1971 to 2002, and complements other collections compiled by Palmquist and held by the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. The collection includes material by professional and amateur photographers and documents aspects of photography from the capture of images through the production of a variety of photographic objects, as well as the marketing and storage of photographs.
Palmquist, Peter E.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Peter Palmquist on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana and Walter McClintock Memorial Fund, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Biographical information and photographic materials related to women photographers are included in the Peter Palmquist Collection of Women in Photography (WA MSS S-2600). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Biographical information and photographic materials related to male photographers active in the western United States are included in the Peter E. Palmquist Collection of Male Photographers in the American West (WA MSS S-2733). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Biographical information and photographic materials related to male photographers active in Humboldt County, California, are included in the Peter Palmquist Collection of Humboldt County, California, Male Photographers (WA MSS S-2670). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Cased photographs are included in the Peter Palmquist Cased Photographs Collection (WA Photos 402). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Stereograph cards that depict California are included in the Peter E. Palmquist Collection of Stereographs of California (WA Photos 494). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Books and periodicals formerly in the personal library of Peter Palmquist are accessible via the library catalog by searching for the search string: "Palmquist, Peter E., Ownership."
Peter E. Palmquist (1936-2003)
A photographer, collector, and historian of photography, Peter Eric Palmquist was born in Oakland, California on September 23, 1936. In 1944, he moved with his family to Ferndale, California, and he spent most of his life in Humboldt County. During adolescence, Palmquist trained himself in photography. He served in the United States Army as a photographer from 1955 to 1959, mainly with the Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers Europe in Paris, France. Palmquist worked briefly as a photographer for the state government of California from 1959 to 1961. From 1961 until his retirement in 1989, Palmquist worked as a staff photographer for Humboldt State University, Arcata, California, where he also graduated with a Bachelor of Arts degree in Art in 1965.
From 1971 until his death, Palmquist collected textual materials and hundreds of thousands of photographic items documenting the practice and occupation of photography from its beginning through the turn of the twenty-first century. He had particular interest in early California photographers, photographers of the American West, and women photographers.
A self-trained researcher and historian of photography, Palmquist organized more than one hundred exhibitions and wrote more than three hundred articles and a hundred monographs. He was a founding editor of The Daguerreian Annual, and a president of the National Stereoscopic Association.
Palmquist died January 13, 2003, in Oakland.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents photography and photographic formats, circa 1838-1999, which Peter Palmquist collected from 1971 to 2002, and complements other collections compiled by Palmquist and held by the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. The collection includes material by professional and amateur photographers and documents aspects of photography from the capture of images through the production of a variety of photographic objects, as well as the marketing and storage of photographs.
The collection is particularly strong in documenting photographic formats. It contains many examples of tintypes and photograph buttons, as well as samples of autochromes, crayon enlargements, greeting cards, jewelry, memorial cards, opalotypes, photographic transparencies, playing cards, stamp photographs, stanhopes, stereograph cards, and wanted posters. The collection also includes examples of photographically illustrated realia, including boxes, cutting tools, paperweights, tobacciana, trays, and writing equipment.
The collection includes about 750 photographic prints by photographers not included in other collections compiled by Palmquist, including itinerant photographers and male photographers working east of the Mississippi River in the United States, as well as male photographers working outside of the United States. It also includes groups of photographic prints that depict celebrities and children, as well as photographs on a variety of subjects by unidentified photographers
Printed material in the collection includes primary documents and secondary research material about photography and photographic formats, as well as examples of advertising for photographers, photographic suppliers, and photographic organizations.
Arrangement
Organized into nine series: I. Research Volumes and Printed Material, circa 1970-1999. II. Printed Material, circa 1846-1994. III. Photographic Processing Material, circa 1875-circa 1993. IV. Photographs by Format, circa 1855-1940. V. Photographic Prints by Male Photographers, circa 1860-circa 1930. VI. Photographic Prints by Subject, circa 1855-circa 1950. VII. Photographs by Unidentified Photographers, circa 1838-circa 1950. VIII. Realia with Photographs, circa 1850-circa 1950. IX. Housing for Photographs, 1862-1931.
Celebrities -- Pictorial works; Children -- Pictorial works; Photographers; Photographic industry; Photography, Stereoscopic; Photography; Photography -- History; Autochromes (photographs); Black-and-white transparencies; Buttons (information artifacts); Crayon enlargements; Greeting cards; Jewelry; Memorial cards; Opalotypes; Paperweights; Photographic prints; Playing cards; Realia; Stanhopes (photographs); Stereographs; Tintypes (prints); Trays; Wanted posters; Palmquist, Peter E.
- Research Volumes, circa 1846-1999; Series I; 4.8; (23 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into three subseries: General Photography, Stereographs, and Panoramas.
  Scope and Contents
  This subseries chiefly consists of notes and photocopies of secondary material about photography, as well as stereographs and panoramas, compiled by Palmquist, which he then bound into volumes.
  - General Photography
    - Photographic History Notes and Gleanings, compiled by Peter E. Palmquist, 1971-1999
      - Volume 1: General Photography; Mobile Darkrooms, Photo Cars, and Tents; Studios; Articles in a Series, 1971-1999 (Box 1)
      - Volume 2: Fine Arts and Miscellaneous Holdings, 1971-1999 (Box 2)
      - Volume 3: Collection of Bibliographies and Indexes, 1971-1999 (Box 3)
      - Volume 4: Ambrotype to X-Ray, 1971-1999 (Box 4)
      - Volume 5: Stereographs, 1971-1999 (Box 5)
      - Volume 6: Miscellaneous, including Button, Stamp, and Medallion Photography; Silhouettes; and Odd, 1971-1999 (Box 6)
      - Volume 7: Oversized Photographs, Panoramas, Photographs of the Sky, Moon, and Sun; Kite Photography, 1971-1999 (Box 7)
      - Volume 8: Notes from Journals and Directories, and Photographically Illustrated Books, 1971-1999 (Box 8)
    - Photographic Technology Notes, compiled by Peter E. Palmquist
      - Volume 1: Prehistory and Chronology of Photographic Inventories (Box 9)
      - Volume 2: The Daguerreotype (Box 10)
      - Volume 3: The Daguerreotype, Miscellaneous Articles and Notes (Box 11)
      - Volume 4: The Daguerreotype, Miscellaneous Collections (Box 12)
    - Historic Photographs, Miscellaneous Articles on Dating, Collecting, and Investing, compiled by Peter E. Palmquist (Box 13)
    - Portrait Photography: Camera Techniques, Darkroom and Studio Construction, Types of Portraiture, Studio Props and Backdrops, Retouching, and Other Miscellaneous Notes, compiled by Peter E. Palmquist (Box 14)
    - Rettenmaier, Deidre. Cataloging Photographic Collections: Defining the Stylistic Parameters of Cabinet Card Photographs., 1993 May (Box 15)
      General note
      Thesis (Master of Arts), San Francisco State University
    - Camera Clubs and Organizations, Miscellaneous Accounts and Resources, compiled by Peter E. Palmquist (Box 16)
    - Aesthetics and Photography, Miscellaneous Writings, compiled by Peter E. Palmquist (Box 17)
  - Stereographs
    - Stereographs, Miscellaneous Notes and Articles, compiled by Peter E. Palmquist (Box 18)
    - Wright, Robert. United States Stereo Photographers and Publishers., circa 1970 (Box 19)
    - Wilburn, John, and T. K. Treadwell. Stereoview Back-Lists. (Bryan, Texas: National Stereoscopic Association), 1984 (Box 20)
    - Southall, Thomas W. "The Kilburn Brothers Stereoscopic View Company", 1977 (Box 21)
      Thesis (Master of Arts), University of New Mexico
    - Griscom, Andrew. A Preliminary Classification of Kilburn Stereoview Cards of the White Mountain Region of New Hampshire, 1985 (Box 22)
  - Panoramas
    - Painted Panoramas and Related Notes (Box 23)
    - McGinnis, Karin Hertel. "Moving Right Along: Nineteenth Century Panorama Painting in the United States", 1983 (Box 24)
      Thesis (Ph. D.), University of Minnesota
    - Avery, Kevin J. "The Panorama and its Manifestation in American Landscape Painting, 1795-1870", 1995 (Box 25)
      Thesis (Ph. D.), Columbia University
- Printed Material, circa 1846-1994; Series II; 1.9; (17 boxes)
  Series II is organized into two subseries: Research Volumes, Printed Material about Photographers and Photography, and Printed Material about Photographic Formats.
  This series printed material Palmquist collected that documents photographers, photography, and photographic formats.
  - Printed Material about Photographers and Photography
    This subseries consists chiefly of printed material used in advertising by photographers, photographic suppliers, photography magazines, photographic publishers, and photographic clubs and associations, as well as graphic representations of photographers and articles about photography.
    Organized under seven headings: Advertising for Photographers, Advertising for Photographic Suppliers, Advertising for Photography Magazines and Publishers, Photography Clubs and Associations, Photography Schools, and Cartoons and Engravings about Photography and Visual Arts, and Articles about Photography.
    - Advertising for Photographers
      Arranged alphabetically by photographer or firm, followed by listings from city directories.
      - Ames Photo Studio, New York City, circa 1915 (Box 26, Folder 1)
      - Brooklyn Art Union, New York City, circa 1892 (Box 26, Folder 2)
      - California Pacific International Exposition, Official Photographer, San Diego, California, 1936 (Box 26, Folder 3)
      - Cavern Supply Company, Carlsbad, New Mexico, circa 1930 (Box 26, Folder 4)
      - Chicago Portrait Company, Chicago, Illinois, 1902-1903 (Box 26, Folder 5)
      - Cook, Leander, traveling photographer active in Massachusetts, circa 1865 (Box 26, Folder 6)
      - E. H. Roberts Portrait Co., Kansas City, Missouri, circa 1916-1919 (Box 26, Folder 7)
      - Everett Department Store, Everett, Washington, circa 1921-1922 (Box 26, Folder 8)
      - F. H. Williams & Company, circa 1875 (Box 26, Folder 9)
      - Fegenbush & Schnell, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1876 (Box 26, Folder 10)
      - Flag Studio, Pasadena, California, circa 1945 (Box 26, Folder 11)
        Aluminum trade token that served as advertising for the studio, as well as a rebate for purchasing Kodak film
      - Fleet Photo, circa 1935 (Box 26, Folder 12)
      - Fox, J. P., Providence, Rhode Island, circa 1890 (Box 26, Folder 13)
      - General Mills, Minnesota, 1958 (Box 26, Folder 14)
      - George P. Hall & Son, New York City, 1900 (Box 26, Folder 15)
      - Gihon, John Lawrence, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, circa 1865 (Box 26, Folder 16)
      - Moore, Henry P., Concord, New Hampshire, circa 1875 (Box 26, Folder 17)
      - Olmsted's Art Studio, 1917 (Box 26, Folder 18)
      - Price, J. C., New Philadelphia, Ohio, circa 1865 (Box 26, Folder 19)
      - Selby & McCauley, Baltimore, Maryland, circa 1865 (Box 26, Folder 20)
      - Starr, Professor, New York City, circa 1865 (Box 26, Folder 21)
      - Various photographers from city directories
        - Boston, Massachusetts, 1876 (Box 26, Folder 22)
        - Brooklyn, New York, 1876 (Box 26, Folder 23)
        - Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1876 (Box 26, Folder 24)
      - Unidentified photographers, circa 1860-circa 1925 (Box 26, Folder 25)
      - Oversize
        - Pano-diorama of the Arctic voyages of Elisha Kane, Phoenix Hall, Boston, Massachusetts, 1858? April 9-15 (Box 27 (Oversize), Folder 26)
        - Moore's Great Chemical Heliopticon, Beekman Hill Methodist Episcopal Sabbath School, New York City, 1866 December 27-28 (Box 27 (Oversize), Folder 27)
        - Heliopticon exhibition, Trinity Methodist Episcopal Church, New York City, 1867 October 31-November 1 (Box 27 (Oversize), Folder 28)
        - G. Sommer & Figlio, Naples, Italy, circa 1900 (Box 27 (Oversize), Folder 29)
    - Advertising for Photographic Suppliers
      Arranged alphabetically by firm.
      - Bourges Inc., New York City, circa 1950 (Box 28, Folder 30)
      - Denny Manufacturing Company, Mobile, Alabama, 1994 December (Box 28, Folder 31)
      - E. & H. T. Anthony, New York City, 1857-circa 1897 (Box 28, Folder 32)
      - Eastman Kodak, Rochester, New York, 1905-1914 (Box 28, Folder 33)
      - Fleischner, Philip, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, circa 1876 (Box 28, Folder 34)
      - Fuji Photo Film Co., Tokyo, Japan, circa 1952 (Box 28, Folder 35)
      - Ilotype Company, New Brighton, New York, circa 1895 (Box 28, Folder 36)
      - Johnson & Sons, London, England, 1925 (Box 28, Folder 37)
      - Lawrence Photo Supply, Wichita, Kansas, circa 1960 (Box 28, Folder 38)
      - Lookies, circa 1930 (Box 28, Folder 39)
      - Pho-Tak Corporation, Chicago, Illinois, circa 1950 (Box 28, Folder 40)
      - Polaroid Corporation, Minnetonka, Minnesota, 1954-1955 (Box 28, Folder 41)
      - Scales, James, Boston, Massachusetts, circa 1880-circa 1885 (Box 28, Folder 42)
      - Scovill Manufacturing Company, New York City, circa 1846-circa 1856 (Box 28, Folder 43)
        Copper trade token advertisement for the company
      - Sears, Roebuck, & Co., circa 1930 (Box 28, Folder 44)
      - Success Postal Card Company, New York City, circa 1910-circa 1915 (Box 28, Folder 45)
      - Trifet, F., Boston, Massachusetts, circa 1880 (Box 28, Folder 46)
      - Western Movie Supply Company, San Francisco, California, 1955 (Box 28, Folder 47)
      - Unidentified suppliers, circa 1900-circa 1950 (Box 28, Folder 48)
      - Oversize
        - Advertisements in The Youth's Companion, 1890 May 22-July 3 (Box 29 (Oversize), Folder 49-50)
        - Minifilm Camera Corporation, New York City, 1949 November-December (Box 29 (Oversize), Folder 51)
    - Advertising for Photography Magazines and Publishers
      Arranged alphabetically by firm or publication.
      - Agfa Ansco (Box 30, Folder 52)
      - Amateur Photographer (Box 30, Folder 53)
      - American Photographic Publishing Co. (Box 30, Folder 54)
      - American Photography (Box 30, Folder 55)
      - The Camera (Box 30, Folder 56)
      - Camera Craft Publishing Co. (Box 30, Folder 57)
      - De Capo Press (Box 30, Folder 58)
      - E. & H. T. Anthony & Co. (Box 30, Folder 59)
      - Eastman Kodak (Box 30, Folder 60)
      - Edward L. Wilson (Box 30, Folder 61)
      - Friends of Photography (Box 30, Folder 62)
      - Graphic Antiquarian Newsletter (Box 30, Folder 63)
      - Infill/Phot (Box 30, Folder 64)
      - Infinity (Box 30, Folder 65)
      - Minicam (Box 30, Folder 66)
      - Modern Photography (Box 30, Folder 67)
      - Morgan & Morgan (Box 30, Folder 68)
      - Photo Technique (Box 30, Folder 69)
      - Photo-Forum (Box 30, Folder 70)
      - Photo-Graphic (Box 30, Folder 71)
      - Photographic Times-Bulletin Publishing Association (Box 30, Folder 72)
      - Pictorial Photographers of America (Box 30, Folder 73)
      - Popular Photography (Box 30, Folder 74)
      - Sam C. Partridge (Box 30, Folder 75)
      - Snap Shots (Box 30, Folder 76)
      - Tennant & Ward (Box 30, Folder 77)
      - U.S. Camera Publishing Co. (Box 30, Folder 78)
    - Photography Clubs and Associations
      This component includes advertising and other printed material related to photography clubs and associations.
      Arranged alphabetically by club or association.
      - 184 Club, Camera Club, circa 1967-1968 (Box 31, Folder 79)
      - California Camera Club (Box 31, Folder 80)
      - Camera Collectors Association, circa 1972 (Box 31, Folder 81)
      - Colorado Photographers' Association, circa 1939 (Box 31, Folder 82)
      - George Eastman House Associates (Box 31, Folder 83)
      - International Photographic Association (Box 31, Folder 84)
      - Japanese Camera Club of San Francisco, circa 1928 (Box 31, Folder 85)
      - Master Photo Finishers of America, circa 1942 (Box 31, Folder 86)
      - Oakland Camera Club, circa 1967-68 (Box 31, Folder 87)
      - Photographers' Association of America (Box 31, Folder 88)
      - Photographic Historical Society of New York (Box 31, Folder 89)
      - Royal Photographic Society of Great Britain (Box 31, Folder 90)
      - Volunteer Service Photographers, circa 1950 (Box 31, Folder 91)
    - Photography Schools
      This subseries includes advertising and other printed material related to photography schools.
      Arranged alphabetically by photography school.
      - Ansco, Binghamton, New York (Box 32, Folder 92)
      - Forest Gate School of Photography, Essex, England (Box 32, Folder 93)
      - Illinois College of Photography, Effingham, Illinois (Box 32, Folder 94)
      - National Educational Alliance, New York, New York (Box 32, Folder 95)
      - National Home Study Council, Washington, DC (Box 32, Folder 96)
      - New York Institute of Photography, Brooklyn, New York (Box 32, Folder 97)
      - Photographic Center of Monterey Peninsula, Carmel, California (Box 32, Folder 98)
      - Rochester Athenaeum and Mechanics Institute, Rochester, New York (Box 32, Folder 99)
      - School of Modern Photography, Little Falls, New Jersey (Box 32, Folder 100)
      - "Schools of Photography." Photo-Era. 44 (1920): 33, 1920 January (Box 32, Folder 101)
    - Cartoons and Engravings about Photography and Visual Arts
      This subseries consists of cartoons and engravings that graphically depict photographers or aspects of photography.
      Arranged chronologically.
      - "Foolish Folks. All Fool's Day Sketches." Harper's New Monthly Magazine, 1856 April (Box 33, Folder 102)
      - "Experiments in Photography." Harper's New Monthly Magazine, 1856 August (Box 33, Folder 103)
      - "Family Daguerreotypes, Found Every Where." Harper's New Monthly Magazine, 1857 July (Box 33, Folder 104)
      - "Noodles's Attempts at Suicide." Harper's New Monthly Magazine, 1859 February (Box 33, Folder 105)
      - "Stereoscopic Slides." Harper's New Monthly Magazine, 1860 October (Box 33, Folder 106)
      - "A Few Cartes de Visite." Harper's New Monthly Magazine, 1863 April (Box 33, Folder 107)
      - McIntire, Ted. "The Photographer's First Reader." Camera Craft. 36.1 (1929): 39, 1929 January (Box 33, Folder 108)
      - Sagendorf, F. C. "History of Photography." Popular Photography, 1938-1940 (Box 33, Folder 109)
      - Burns, T. A. "Crow Hill Art School", 1897 (Box 33, Folder 110)
        Probably refers to the Crow Hill Community, Brooklyn, New York
      - "This Was Photography, No. 1." Popular Photography., 1944 July (Box 33, Folder 111)
      - Peanuts; comic strip includes the character Snoopy using a video camera, 1989 October 29 (Box 33, Folder 112)
      - Oversize
        - Thomas, W., Engraving based on the painting, "The Photographer," by William Bromley, Illustrated London News, 1864 May 28 (Box 34 (Oversize), Folder 113)
        - Forbes, Edwin Austin, "Sitting for his Portrait." Hearth and Home, 1873 June 21 (Box 34 (Oversize), Folder 114)
        - Opper, Frederick Burr, "The Amateur Photographer in the Country," Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, 1886 August 7 (Box 34 (Oversize), Folder 115)
    - Articles about Photography
      - "The Stereoscope, Psuedoscope, and Solid Daguerreotypes," Illustrated London News, 1852 January 24 (Box 35 (Oversize), Folder 116)
      - "A Photographic Gun," Harper's Weekly, 1882 May 27 (Box 35 (Oversize), Folder 117)
      - "How New York Looks from a Kite," New York World Monthly, 1895 December (Box 35 (Oversize), Folder 118)
      - "Under-water Cinematography: Filming Fish and Crustaceans," Illustrated London News, 1922 August 12 (Box 35 (Oversize), Folder 119)
  - Printed Material about Photographic Formats
    This subseries includes printed material about photographic formats, including advertising, instruction sheets, and other related items.
    Organized under four headings: Stereoscopic Photography Literature, Photograph Button Literature, Advertising for Photographic Novelties, and Photographic Product Literature and Instruction Sheets.
    - Stereoscopic Photography Literature
      Arranged alphabetically.
      - 3-D Extra, 1987 July 27 (Box 36, Folder 120)
        In German
      - 3-D Foto World Catalogue (Box 36, Folder 121)
      - 3-D Glasses. Federal Express (Box 36, Folder 122)
      - 3-D Glasses. National Stereoscopic Association (Box 36, Folder 123)
      - 3-D Glasses. New Dimensions in Retina, 1993 (Box 36, Folder 124)
      - 3-D Glasses. Reel 3-D Enterprises (Box 36, Folder 125)
      - 3-D Slide Viewer. Stereo Magniscope, Inc. (Box 36, Folder 126)
      - 3-Dimensional Picture Cards. American History Series (Box 36, Folder 127)
      - 3-Dimensional Picture Cards. Animal Series (Box 36, Folder 128)
      - Alderson, Tony. "3D Zomoid Illustories in the Miracle of Freevision.", 1985 (Box 36, Folder 129)
      - Allphin, Willard. "Stereo Ain't Dead?" Modern Photography. (1970): 80-81, 100, 124-125, 141., 1970 April (Box 36, Folder 130)
      - Bangert, Ethel. "Stereoscopic Mania." Relics. 1.4 (1968): 8-9. (Box 36, Folder 131)
      - "The Battle of Gettysburg in 3-D", 1963 (Box 36, Folder 132)
      - Bell and Howell. Instruction booklet for a stereo camera. (Box 36, Folder 133)
      - The California Museum of Photography. "Stereo Cameras and Viewers.", 1980 (Box 36, Folder 134)
      - Chandler, Arthur, and Wayne Pope. "Stereo Views of the Golden Era in San Francisco", 1976 (Box 36, Folder 135)
      - Cotton, Walter Scott, and Richard W. Strong. "Stereo-Photography." The Camera. 69.7 (1947): 81-96., 1947 July (Box 36, Folder 136)
      - Crockwell, Douglass. "Convinced Stereo is Still Alive..." Popular Photography. 36.94 (1960): 81, 102., 1960 April (Box 36, Folder 137)
      - D. Appleton and Co. Catalogue of Photo-Lithographic views (Box 36, Folder 138)
      - "The Deadly Stereoscope." The Literary Digest. 61.4 (1919): 121-123., 1919 April (Box 36, Folder 139)